[开场音乐]
收音检查1, 2...1, 2, 3, 4...敏捷的棕色狐狸跳过了懒狗...
Check 1,2 Check 1,2 1,2,3,4 The quick brown fox jumps over the lazy dog
这里是React播客，我是小钱
This is react podcast I'm chantastic
今天我们逆溯时光，回到React的起源
today we're going back, way back, back to the beginning of react
10年以后的今天回顾React的发展
10 years in the rear view mirror it may
感觉React的成功似乎是注定的
feel like react was always going to
毕竟这是一个由Facebook推出的明星框架，光环加身，似乎不可能失败
succeed did a framework by Facebook was too big to fail but this isn't that kind
但今天的故事会告诉你事情并没有那么简单
of story in fact there were many times
事实上在React发展历程的很多时间点，这个框架都看起来要失败
in reacts history where it seemed like it wasn't going to succeed at all
所以10年间到底发生了什么，让React从被人嫌弃到大受欢迎
so what happened how did react go in 10 years from looking Dead on Arrival to
乃至成为今天居于统治地位的JavaScript框架
becoming the dominant front-end JavaScript framework that it is today
故事要从2011年的Facebook讲起
it starts at Facebook in 2011
JQuery和backbone.js在前端领域正如日中天
jQuery and backbone are dominating front-end
但是更富有自己独特哲学的工具，比如Ember.js, AngularJS, Knockout.js已经出道
JavaScript but more opinionated tools like Ember angular knockout are already on the scene
在技术宅之外的世界中，《江南Style》刚被上传到Youtube
In the outside world Gangnam Style has just been uploaded to
《Call me maybe》是第一热歌
YouTube Call Me Maybe is topping the charts and the freshest meme is the
当时最新的迷因是过于黏人的女朋友
overly attached girlfriend in Internet
也就是说按照互联网纪年，从React诞生到现在，一个永恒已经过去了
years it's basically been an eternity
那么让我们系好安全带，打开勿扰模式，观赏下面这个精彩的的菜狗逆袭故事
so strap in set yourself away enable that do not disturb because this is quite the Underdog Story
[音乐]
我发现这个摄像机有个红色提示灯，这个没有
I think this camera has a red light, but this one doesn't
[Applause]
[Music]
把这个挂在衣服上就行
just keep it on with this
收音测试1, 2...
testing one two testing
[Music]
foreign
当拿到Facebook offer的时候我非常激动，我兴奋地告诉了妈妈
work at Facebook I told my mom I was like really excited The Social Network
当时《社交网络》这部电影刚刚上映，她看过电影后非常不鼓励我进入Facebook工作
the movie had just come out and she had you know seen it recently and she was actively discouraging me from joining
她的理由是扎克伯格看起来不是一个好孩子
because she was like Mark Zuckerberg doesn't seem like a very nice boy
我还在那工作的那段时间，Facebook是有点特别的，那种特别是一去不返了
Facebook in the time I was there was I don't think they'll be anything like it ever again it was certainly not like
可以确定的是当时的Facebook和我此前工作的任何一家公司都不一样
anything that I had experienced before
我加入Facebook几个月以后，侃爷拜访了Facebook园区
in fact just a couple months after I joined Kanye West came to visit
他爬上了食堂的桌子，现场rap了一段
Facebook's campus and he got up on a table in the cafe and you know wrapped a
我当时试图向一个刚刚毕业的同事解释，
few bars and I was working mostly with this guy who had just graduated from
我在这个行业工作了10多年，这种事情从来没有发生过,
college and I was trying to explain to him you know I've worked these crap jobs in software at that point had been like
像这样的事情从来没有在软件工程师行业发生过
10 or 15 years nothing like this ever happens not to software Engineers you're
[侃爷rap中]
my stressing your mama sues Mama say
Mama say Mama Don the son
JavsScript当时正经历一场对自身存在意义的怀疑
JavaScript at the time I think was going through this little bit of an existential crisis as to
比如说它是不是一门真正的编程语言
whether it was like a real programming language
还是说仅仅是一门玩具语言
or a toy programming language and so
所以当时有很多发展的趋势
there was a lot of churn so you had
JQuery, mootools都很流行
jQuery was popular and moo tools was
有很多受欢迎的框架激烈竞争市场份额
popular and there was so many different like warring Frameworks to try to get
这些工具之间有很多相似性，也各有其擅长的场景
the Mind share and there's a lot of similarities between them but each one had its kind of bespoke differences and
但是它们中间没有一个在构造复杂用户界面和应用时表现特别突出
none of them were actually really fantastic for building really kind of complicated user interfaces and apps
当时的趋势是应用越来越复杂，需要做的事情也越来越多
there was this trend towards more sophisticated applications that do more
当时在Facebook我们的主要技术栈依然是服务端渲染
stuff and at Facebook we still had a primarily sort of server rendered technology stack which
因为很长一段时间内，我们都致力于减小不断增大的前端应用中的JavsScript产物体积
um you know one of the things that we fought against for a really long time was just growing JavaScript bundle sizes
而这是因为当我们在浏览器中实现越来越多的功能以后，前端应用变得越来越慢
so as we moved more and more stuff to the client the client got slower and
也就是说当时我们一直在往CSR-SSR这个天平的SSR端靠近，尽量减少客户端JavaScript体积
slower so we actually swung the pendulum towards server-side rendering and towards you know minimal amounts of JavaScript for a while and there was
当时的感觉是我们知道浏览器端的开发模式已经不能满足新的需求
this feeling that we knew that what we were doing for client-side development
但是我们同时感到服务端技术也不能彻底解决问题
wasn't working but also that server side wasn't going to get us all the way there
这差不多就是React诞生前的技术环境
so I think that was the kind of environment that react came out of
2010年加入Facebook之前，我做了很多开源工作，特别是在JavsScript领域
I joined Facebook back in 2010 I've been doing a lot of Open Source work particularly in the JavaScript world I
我曾经是dojo.js toolkit委员会成员，
was a committer on the dojo.js toolkit back in the day which is one of the the
dojo.js，jQuery和prototype都是JavaScript运动的先声
granddaddies of the JavaScript movement along with prototype and jQuery
我在Facebook的头两年都在移动团队
I spent my first two years of Facebook on the mobile team
当时我们已经开始着力和Apple以及Google的竞争
we had started off a big push to compete with Apple and Google and we thought
我们认为我们最大的机会在于直接投入web领域
that our best chance of success as a company was to go directly to the web
着力于建设HTML5生态
and really push to build out the HTML5
作为战略的一部分，我和另外两位工程师Vladimir和Bailey
ecosystem so as part of that we developed myself two other Engineers called Vladimir
创建了一个叫做Bolt.js的JS框架，叫这个名字是因为我们
khalestikov and will Bailey built a framework called bolt JS so named
将几项我们几个喜欢的技术整合固定在一起，形成了这个框架
because we bolted together a bunch of things that each of us liked
（bolt做动词有"用螺丝固定"的意思）
Bolt.js基本上是Facebook对客户端MVC架构的一种实现
bolt was basically more or less Facebook's implementation of a client's
对比当时的一些MVC框架比如Backbone.js，我认为Bolt.js可能是一种更好的MVC实现
head MVC I think it was like a pretty good version maybe a better version of things like backbone and a couple of other Frameworks that had existed at the
但是它带有Facebook业务特有的一些限制
time but it was born from a place of the specific constraints of Facebook
"它将是你Facebook体验的核心"
it's the heart of your Facebook experience
"经过彻底的重新思考"
completely rethought from the ground up
“和一年的精心打磨”
we've been working on it all year
"它就是Timeline(时间线功能)"
and we're calling it timeline
Facebook属于第一批体验重于其他一切的产品
Facebook was one of the first big products that was really an experience more than anything else
你不会用Facebook来买日用品或者买票
you're not trying to buy groceries or get tickets or anything like that on
用户只是想上去找点乐子
Facebook you really just want to be entertained and as such you know the
因此它的用户界面需要让人愉悦
user interface itself needs to be really
Bolt.js不是一系列分散工具的集合
pleasing bolt was not a tool belt it was
而是一个真正的应用开发框架，它被设计用来构建复杂，有丰富交互的应用
truly a application development framework something designed and meant to build complicated interactive rich
事实上，它也确实被当时的Facebook用来开发非常复杂的真实世界应用
apps and was being used to build pretty complicated very real products at Facebook at the time
最后的发展是我们基本上需要用Bolt.js来重构Facebook的大部分应用
we ended up having to essentially replicate most of Facebook
不管是时间线，聊天，还是新闻流，以及整个相册应用
all the various apps be it timeline chat news feed we had a whole photos app that
整个团队快速扩张
we built and so obviously the team had to expand greatly like that so I think
在某个时刻团队大概有25个工程师，有的做bolt本身的开发，有的做基于bolt的应用开发
at some point we probably had maybe 25 Engineers working on all this between building bold and building apps built on
这还仅限于移动团队
Bold and that's just on the mobile team
Bolt从来就不是问题所在，有问题的是当时应用开发的架构
bolt was never the problem it was the architecture that would eventually break
当时的架构是压倒骆驼的最后一根稻草
down for us as the the product itself
随着产品逐渐复杂和团队人数的增多，
got more complex and as we added more Engineers to the team we didn't hit a
变更产品功能变得越来越困难
wall but it started to get really really hard to make changes and so you know
这时候广告团队的Jordan对现状发出了疑问:
that was around the time that Jordan was on the ads team and he's like I wonder
"难道没有更好的开发方式吗?"
there's got to be a better way
[谁是Jordan Walke?]
不是这个
Jordan是一个谜一样的人物
Jordan is an enigmatic figure he uh he's a
他行事隐秘，我对他所知不多
little secretive so there's not much that I know about him
Jordan和我一直没有特别进入公共视野，特别是Jordan，
从React的早期开始他就远离了关注的焦点
Jordan and I aren't necessarily we haven't necessarily been in the spotlight much especially Jordan kind of shied away from spotlights since the early days
Jordan当时是广告团队的一名工程师
Jordan was a product engineer at the time working on ads and ads has one of
广告在当时是横跨Facebook所有业务中UI最为复杂的
the most complicated pieces of UI across all of Facebook at the moment
在应用复杂性方面，当时的广告团队正在逼近没有React框架时所能做到的极限
on the as team they were hitting much you know really hitting the limits of what you can do without react uh
当时的开发者已经很难把屏幕上的UI和对应的代码联系起来，并理解代码的作用
complexity wise and just the developers ability to hold in their head and understand a bit of code that somebody else wrote and you know look at the screen and say okay this code is doing that and I need to know why
Jordan有很多有趣的想法，比如对于Blot的函数式使用
and Jordan had a lot of very interesting ideas around how you could take what we had done in both and make it much more functional
如何让Blot更容易地规模化应用，以便让人更容易理解大型应用
and make it more um ability to make it easier for it to scale with, people's ability to understand large
所以我们有很多持续进行的讨论
applications and so we had a lot of ongoing dialogue and he would come back
我们会来来回回探讨可以如何改变Blot
and forth to us with various ideas how to change it
我记得React早期的名字其中一直就是FBlot，意思是函数式Blot
I think one of the original names for react was F bolt which is functional Bolt
[音乐]
Jordan意识到有一种更容易的方式，可以解决Blot中的一些棘手问题
to do it to solve some of the tricky Parts in bolts in an easier way so what
所以Jordan的思路是（至少他是这么告诉我的）
Jordan decided to do or at least the story that he had told me was
不管应用中发生了什么改变，
不管是API状态变动，还是用户输入了什么，我们都销毁掉所有UI，然后重新渲染一切
hey wouldn't it be easier if any time anything happened in the app API State changes user type something we just blow away the entire UI and we re-render all of it
对比当时的框架，那时流行的是数据双向绑定
if you look at what every other framework was doing at the time it was called two-way data binding and this was
但Jordan说忘记数据绑定吧，我们不再操心那个了
not that it was like forget about data binding we're not going to do that at all
新的做法是任何时刻发生任何变动，我们都重新渲染整个UI
anytime anything changes we're just going to re-render
当然旁边有个注脚，我们不会真的重新渲染整个UI，并且我们会尽可能少地重新渲染
and then there's an asterisk which says well we're not going to remember everything we're going to try to render
但是概念上，我们不会再手动维护视图和模型之间的关系
as little as possible but conceptually we're not going to manage these relationships between views and models
概念上我们会...(直接销毁之前的视图，并根据新的数据状态生成新的视图)
we're just gonna
坦白说，我那时觉得这是一个疯狂的想法，而且当时我也对框架持怀疑态度
honestly I thought it was completely crazy at the time I was really down on
我觉得这个想法不会成功
Frameworks in general and I thought there was no way that was going to work
对于很多人来说Jordan的想法过于魔法，超出了他们对于现实的认知
to many people that seemed like magic it was so far outside of everybody's idea of how things should work and do work
(我们花费了)很多精力去说服他们
that um yeah it took a lot of commenting
[Music]
我已经在Facebook工作10年了
I've been working at Facebook for 10 years now
曾经我和一个叫Jordan Walke的人碰过面
I met this person called Jordan walk
背景是有人告诉我Jordan有一个关于JS的有趣项目，我可能会对其感兴趣
some people told me like he had an interesting project about JavaScript and I may be interested and so I had this
所以我和他约了一个会，在会议的开始他问了我一个问题：
meeting with him and uh one thing he asked me at the beginning of the meeting
“前端开发目前最困难的事情是什么？”
was what is the most difficult thing to do in the front end right now and I mean I was six months out of
我那时刚毕业6个月，我说我不知道，他告诉我是“(UI的)更新”
school I was like I don't know and the thing he told me is updates you need to
你需要找到要更新的dom节点，选择合适的事件后增加/移除事件回调等等这些
find the dumb node that is going to change you need to like change the listener to like the Click event and like remove it and like do all of this
整个过程相当繁琐，Facebook广告业务代码的大量bug都在这个过程中产生
which is like pretty complicated and then this was also like a massive source of bugs within the Facebook adbase
我被他说服了，承认道“好吧这大概是最困难的事情”，然后他说他有一个解决方案
I was like okay yeah you're right like this is probably like the hardest thing and it was like I have a solution for this
(我听了他的方案以后)觉得这家伙的想法太疯狂，不会成功，也不会有好的性能表现
I was like okay this guy is crazy like this is never going towards never going to be performance
会议结束过了几个星期我就忘记了这件事
the meeting ended for like a few weeks I forgot about the idea
但是有一个周末我重新考虑了这件事，觉得自己也许应该尝试一下
but uh one weekend I was like okay maybe I should try this like maybe there's something to it
[Music]
加入Facebook之前，我做过一个魔兽世界工会的搜索项目
before joining Facebook I walked on a way to find your guilds in World of
我们需要在20000个工会中搜索到目标
Warcraft and we basically need to search through like 20 000 yields and I did
我做了很多的性能优化工作，以便用户更改搜索过滤条件时能更快给出搜索结果
like a lot of uh performance work to like be the fastest way to display possible when you change all of those filters into this real time
我当时想我花了数月的时间全职优化这个项目
and I was like okay I spent like months full time like working on like making this super
现在让我试一下用React重写会有什么不同
performance let's try it with react and in practice uh it took me like half an
我花了差不多半个小时重写了项目，重写的版本性能不如原版
hour to write it and it was actually like not as performant but like around
但是和原版相差不远，我被结果震惊了
the same order of magnitude as performance and I was like mind blown
从那以后，我就成了React的头号粉丝
and to this day I became like the biggest react fan in the world I was in
之后我在相册团队的所有工作时间我都在使用React，并且尝试在自己的项目上使用
the photos team and like spending all of my working hours like trying to like use
同时也在向其他人布道React，因为我感觉React会改变世界
react on my own project in the photos team evangelizing I felt like it could change the world
它也确实改变了世界
which it did
[Music]
Jordan的项目现在开始逐步取得进展，其他人也开始参与进来
Jordan is making Headway on his project he's gotten others involved and they're seeing the value but not everyone is
但不是所有人都买账，其中一个Facebook的经理认为Jordan的项目分散了员工的精力
impressed one manager started to take notice but saw Jordan's project is a
所以他们让Byron和Jordan会面，告诉他项目需要终止distraction so the athlete Byron to meet with Jordan and put a stop to it
一见面我就知道这次会面会很尴尬奇怪
we get into a room instantly I knew that this was going to be weird
因为我们的态度明显不同，我的态度是我需要理解你的项目到底价值在哪
because we showed up with very different energies so I'm showing up with this like okay Jordan I want to understand what's going on with your
我需要确定它值得长期投入和能带来长远价值，可以解决我们面临的问题
project but I also want to help make sure that we are spending our time well and we're working on things that are gonna have longevity and solving problems we
Jordan却非常兴奋地想给我展示他的demo，推销该项目具有的激动人心的特性
want to have and Jordan came in with like can I show you a demo of what I've been working on like this is so exciting and it does this and it does that and
接近会面尾声的时候我不得不承认我被说服了，他的项目确实有点东西
eventually like towards the end of this meeting with him I had to kind of admit like he had something really compelled like I was now really interested in
我开始希望了解更多的项目细节
learning more about what what he was doing
Jordan最后也表示只有该项目最终会被人们使用的前提下，他才会继续开发下去
so Jordan's pitch to me was like I only want to invest in this and work on it if it's going to be something that
如果管理层决定这不可能，他当然不会继续投入开发，但是他也表示对项目充满了信心
people will use and if that's not going to be the case like sure we're not going to do this he's like but I feel really strongly that all the ways we've been
他认为截至当前所有的UI开发方式都有缺憾
doing UI development up until now have been flawed whether they're a JavaScript
不管是现存的可以完成很多工作的JS框架还是其他久经考验的UI开发模式
library that doesn't quite work for us or whether it's like a 30 year old uh tried and true model for doing UI application development like they all
都受困于同一类基础问题，也就是状态管理
suffer from the same base problem Estate Management
他认为自己的方式(React的前身)是下一步的正确方向
and I think this is the way forward and Lee if you could just like dig into
他说如果你能花点时间再了解尝试一下，然后我们再见面讨论，也许我们会有更清晰的答案
the code and learn more and try it and then come back and we'll talk about this again um then we can figure this out it's like
我说好的好的，于是我研究了他的代码
all right all right and so I did I dug around the code and it was um
一开始发现有点难懂，但是我最终学会了怎么使用
a little hard to understand uh but I eventually got to play with it got to
我用它做了几个小东西，然后总结发现，确实这里有非常有意思的东西
build a couple of things and uh like had to admit coming away that like yes there was something incredibly interesting there and that was how I got sucked into
我就这样成了项目的一员，接下来好几个月都在做相关工作
the project I ended up working on it quite a bit for the the next couple of
Byron给项目带来了一种生机勃勃的设计思维
months Lee brings us like rigor and sort of design mentality to these things that
他帮助React初始的几个版本做了标准化
um really helped with the initial versions of react in terms of standardizing it
将React从一个Facebook的内部项目变成了一个外部世界可以欣赏接受的东西
and turning it from something that was kind of like an ugly baby that it just uh grown up at Facebook to something that really people could approach from around the world
[Music]
当我开始尝试理解React代码库和使用它构建应用的时候，立刻就遇到了几个问题
there were a couple of problems that I faced right away when trying to understand the code base and build something
它所使用的一套工具和思维模型和我之前作为UI工程师接触到的完全不同
Not only was the the set of tools and the mental models really different from what I was used to as a
而且语法，概念，一整套术语都很特别
UI engineer the syntax and the programming just like Concepts involved just the terminology was also really different my takeaway
虽然它的卖点是会让UI开发更简单，但是我却不禁感到使用它非常复杂
was you know okay the whole bid here was that this would be simpler but I can't help but feel like this is really complicated
出于让自己理解它的目的，也是希望能够帮助理清一些概念
mostly as a as a desire for me to understand the model um but also with a hope that it would kind of end up helping resolve some things I
我开始建立一个术语表，将项目涉及的概念一一梳理出来
wanted to build uh like a glossary like what are all the things the concepts and
并确定与其对应的动作行为
then what are all the like actions or like verbs that are going on here and so
我拿着列出的一个个术语去找到Jordan和其他项目组成员，验证相关概念的理解
I I literally just like listed them all out and then I would go back to Jordan I'd go back to other people working on it and ask questions like did I get this
他们会说“对的”“不对”“你想错了，应该这样考虑”等等
right are these definitions right and they go yeah okay no you should really think about it that way and be like okay well that's not how this and it would go
经过多次讨论，我们对概念的理解开始趋于一致
back and forth and back and forth and I'd be honing these definitions and
并且意识到有些概念是重复的，它们应该叫同一个名字
along the way we'd realize like oh this concept and that concept are the same we're going to name them one thing instead of two things
最终经过重新思考的，用新术语描述的组件生命周期出炉了，也就是面向用户的React API经过了一轮重构
so unwinding all of this and essentially writing up what ended up being like a reimagining of the component life cycle and therefore sort of the entire front-facing API for react
项目组成员对这样的变化非常欢迎，我也很高兴
and I was very happy to see like incredible enthusiasm around that Jordan
Jordan说这太棒了，真的帮助理清了概念
was like oh this is amazing this really clarifies the ideas at that point a
那个时候一些其他成员开始加入项目组
handful of other folks had gotten involved with the project too and then I
接下来几个月我都在一点点地完善这些概念，帮助人们理解，在这个过程中极大改变了面向用户的React API
spent sort of the next month or so sort of piece by piece folding those into place and pretty significantly changing the surface API of react in the process
我认为这是React思想的第一次真正传播，它从一个Jordan脑海里的东西变成了一个被整个团队共享的理论
that was I think the first shift from this being a thing that existed mostly in Jordan's head that other people were playing with to a thing that all of a sudden felt owned by the whole team uh
这里说的团队就是受项目愿景吸引的一帮Facebook UI工程师
where team here is like a collection of UI Engineers scattered across Facebook who were sort of bought in on this
现在有了统一的术语以后，如果有人有问题，任何人都可以跳出来回答而不用再仅仅依靠Jordan解答
Vision who now felt that like we now have the same terminology we can use when someone has a question anyone can jump in and answer it rather than only
这就是React思想的第一次传播
Jordan that was the first big shift
[Music]
最开始使用React的几个项目之一是UFI: 统一反馈界面
one of the first projects um that Greg was used for was the ufi the universal feedback interface which
基本上就是每篇贴文下面的喜欢/评论/分享功能
is basically the likes comments and shares at the bottom of each post this
当时还处于Facebook称雄的网络时代，Facebook是连接人群的一大驱动力
was still during Facebook's kind of web era when Facebook on the web was like the sort of Big Driver of Engagement
新闻流功能每天使用的人超过10亿
news feed had a billion people hitting it every day
因此经过了大规模的性能优化
and was massively tuned for performance
用户界面的输入和输出都要求高度的互动
heavily interactive surface both on the input side of course you're like
输入侧有点击喜欢按钮，聊天框中输入内容等
clicking it to add likes you're typing into it to add comments but also on the
输出侧我们希望评论可以实时显示而不需要刷新
receiving side we want comments to come in live so as you're looking at it as a
也就是你盯着网页的时候新的评论会嗖地自己上屏
comment comes in we want it to just pop up right there and there was this
也就是希望用户界面可以表现地像聊天窗口一样即时更新
product desire for that interface to feel almost like a one-off chat thread
当时这种想法非常让人激动
and that was so cool at that time and as
当这个想法被实现以后，人们又想如果一篇贴文可以做到这样，那么对于整个贴文界面是不是也可以做到
that started to work the second thread was well okay if this can work for this really isolated sense of messaging then what if it could work for messaging as a whole
而这又是一项复杂且容易出bug的工作
and this was another really complicated and fraught with bug surface area that
这催生出了React中的一些新想法，JSX语法诞生了，一些如何管理数据的想法出现了
was when a lot of the ideas in react congealed the jsx syntax was introduced and some of the ideas about how to work with data and react sort of were clarified
一些UI工程师和消息团队成员，特别是我们的领头人Jing Chen意识到
a couple of our UI Engineers along with the messaging team if I remember correctly Jing Chen was sort of the champion of this project realized
除了React我们还需要一种全新的方式去思考"状态"
that we needed a completely new way to think about State too
我叫Jing，是Facebook产品基础设施团队的一名软件工程师
so my name is John um and I'm a software engineer and the product infrastructure team at Facebook
Flux是一个围绕着React单向数据流设计的应用架构
is an application architecture designed around react's principle of unidirectional data flow paired with
有了Flux以后，React就可以触及到视图层以外，为整个应用建立模型
flux react could go beyond the view layer to model entire applications this
Flux对状态管理的思考和React对于UI更新的思考不谋而合
shift in how to think about State paired very well with how react was thinking
React由此迈入了一个新的发展阶段，它不再仅仅是一个开发复杂UI的工具
about updating UI and ended up being sort of the next chapter for how to think about react being more than just how do you model complicated UI but how
而逐渐成为一个能够开发整个相当复杂应用的框架
do you model sufficiently complicated applications like this was something
它已经能够管理整个界面，多个触点的交互，跳转导航等等，Flux的出现让React的发展进入新篇章
that expanded the full screen and multiple touch points and had navigation to it and it allowed us to step into
我记得问Jing，“嘿，那个叫React的项目怎么样了，你觉得有戏吗？”
that next chapter I remember asking Jing like hey how's it going with this react stuff you know do you think this is
她给了非常肯定的回答
going to work she's like yeah this is pretty good I'm pretty sure it's gonna
从那开始我对React有了更多信心
work that was when I became more convinced
[很激动和大家分享这条消息：我们已经同意收购Instagram...]
谢谢
thank you
[Music]
Instagram在2012被Facebook收购
Instagram joined Facebook in 2012. I
我记得那个时候React这个名字已经定下来了
think we had started calling it react by
当时有几个Facebook的工程师前往Instagram，帮助他们扩大产品的触及面
then and there was a couple Engineers from Facebook that went to join Instagram to help them expand the
在此之前他们只有iOS和Android应用，现在他们也想拓展到web端
product offering at the time Instagram was just an iOS and an Android app and they wanted to have a web presence as well
foreign
[Music]
我在旧金山生活了11年，生活愉悦，交友很多
11 years in San Francisco it was a really fun made a lot of great friends
然而乡村生活的缓慢步调，平和的氛围更入我心
but the the change of pace out in the in the countryside is is great um it's just very peaceful and nice
我是一毕业就进入了Facebook，大学学了计算机，然后又读了研究生
I went to Facebook straight at school Istudied computer science undergrad and I got a master's degree Facebook was
现在说来你可能不信，那时Facebook还是非常有吸引力的，他们的产品触及到每个人，在校园也非常流行
believe it or not the like cool place to work back in 2010 it was like this great product that like everybody used it was super cool on college campuses and I was
所以能去那里工作我非常激动
really excited to work there
foreign
我当时加入的是视频团队，他们说我们是世界第三大视频网站
I joined Facebook video the pitch was we're the third largest
仅次于Youtube和Daily motion
video site in the world after YouTube and Daily motion I think and there was
现在只有一个工程师在负责该项目，你可以成为二号工程师
like one engineer working on it and like you get to be engineer number two and I
我觉得这太棒了，当时我们和iOS和Android的相册团队紧密合作
was like that sounds pretty cool we worked really closely with the iOS
试图打造一个可以干掉Instagram的产品
photos team in the Android Photos team and we were building an Instagram killer
这个产品就是Facebook Camera，现在已经被人遗忘了
and nobody remembers this but it was called Facebook Camera
有天早上相册团队被通知提前8点到总部，工程副总裁通知Instagram已经被我们收购了，现在大家是同事了
one morning the photo scene got called into the office early they said like be at HQ at 8am and then the VP of engineering was like hey we bought Instagram they're your new co-workers now and
此前两方都互视为最主要的竞争对手
these were like our people that they were like our Fierce competitors you know we looked at them a little bit as the enemy I'm sure they looked at us a little bit as the enemy
Instagram当时是一个很小的团队，他们的核心业务已经打造得非常好
they were a really small team at the time they had their core fundamentals really nailed
但是他们还需要探索很多东西，这些东西他们并没有相应的技术团队去投入
but there was a lot of stuff they needed to figure out that they did not have the team to figure out along with their own
其中一项就是Instagram的web版到底要如何塑造
and a big one of those was what does it mean for Instagram to be on the web
产品的web体验是促进增长的一个重要推动力，所以Instagram的web端变得重要起来
the web experience is really important for driving growth and so this was a pretty important priority and
所以我和一个设计师Michael开始构建Instagram的web端
so me and this Designer Michael lumens started building all the web stuff and that's kind of
从我们开始着手建设网站，使用的就是React
where react enters the pictures when we started developing this website
[Music]
当时我们被要求使用CSR来构建网站，我找到当时由Tom领导的产品基础设施团队寻求帮助
we were given this mandate to use client rendering so I went to the product infrastructure team at Facebook which was run by like Tom Aquino product
基础设施团队的角色就是支持任何需要帮助的团队
infrastructure's role was to support any team that needed help
我们的KPI就是其他团队认可我们的帮助
and do it in a way that you know your key indicators of success are going to be other teams saying yeah that really helped us
咨询Tom他们就像咨询元老院一样，他们会给出建议
you go to them and you kind of consult the Council of Elders and they they give you their recommendation and I
我问道，我们现在要做CSR，你们有什么建议吗？
said hey we need to do client rendering what do we do and the recommendation at
他们说我们也不知道，我们现在有三个CSR选项，也许你应该尝试其中一个
the time was yeah we don't know we've got like three different things that we're working on you should go try one
三个选项如下，一个是Bolt，一个是jshtml
we had uh something called bolt Js there was a second thing called jshtml
还有就是一个叫React的东西
and then there was this this thing called react
Pete跟Jordan讨论了使用React，和我讨论了使用Bolt，但是我觉得他非常喜欢React的函数式思想
you wouldn't spoke to Jordan about using react and he came and talked to me about potentially using both for it but I think he really really liked Jordan's ideas around functional programming
React的核心概念具有非同一般的创造性，和我的内心共鸣
the conceptual model of react was like crazy Innovative and it really really spoke to me
我并不喜欢前端，也不看好前端当时的发展
my background was in distributed systems I was not somebody that loved front end or thought front end was like doing things well
所以我并不在乎此前前端的最佳实践，所以对带着全新开发范式出现的React接受很快，
so the fact that react came in with like a totally Fresh Approach and like didn't really care too much about existing best practices like I was I was on board with that so while
我衡量了三个选项以后选中了React，用它写了Instagram网站的原型，成了最终发布版本的基础
I had evaluated all three I really just dove in on react to build a prototype first and that ended up shipping on instagram.com
这是有史以来React在生产环境的第二次应用，是第一次用React构造端到端整个应用
which was the second use of of reactant production ever and the first use of building a full application end to end in react
那时即使在Facebook内部React也是不为人知的，它像是一个秘密的疯狂科学试验
when I chose react for Instagram it was not well known within Facebook and it was this like kind of crazy science experiment
[对于应用到Instagram网站，当时的React准备好了吗？]
还差得很远
not even close
在Pete开始将React用于Instagram的时候
by the time Instagram was and you know Pete was started playing with it
React已经比之前好太多，但是依然处于早期发展阶段，还需很多迭代改善
uh it was significantly better than it was in the early early stage uh but it still needed a ton of iteration
当时的React和Facebook的基础设施耦合在一起
we had to take this thing that was very much tied to Facebook's infrastructure
所谓的基础设施就是一个巨大的PHP应用
which back then was a big giant PHP application and I had to go get that
我需要将React和Facebook解耦，然后让它配合Instagram的后端django应用
working in a Django application which is a totally different system and what was
这项工作的窍门是不要想一次完成工作，而是让迁移可持续，并且确保迁移的管道正常运转
key was not doing that once but making that a repeatable process and and making sure that that pipeline didn't break
我记得Pete遇到了很多有趣的问题，说明了React还不能拿来做Instagram规模的应用
I think he hit a number of really interesting problems along the way which quite proved the fact that react was not quite ready for that scale
为了解决问题，Pete和他的团队也在这个过程中构建了很多有意思的东西
and along the way Pete and the team that he was working with into that building a lot of really interesting things
[Music]
foreign
早期使用React的几个项目都相当成功
some of these products ended up being fairly successful there were relatively
它们都在较短的开发时间内达成了较高的质量，证明了React是一种有效的开发方式
short time to to deliver a relatively high quality product that show that this model could work
不仅如此，人们开始喜欢使用它，这让React逐渐扩散和起飞
and it was not just that but people liked developing using it and so that kind of spread and took off
特别是使用越来越多以后，人们意识到这是他们喜欢的开发方式
and especially if you got more and more investment they came clear that this was what we wanted to use and
但当时广告团队已经在重度使用Bolt，很多人对Bolt已经非常熟悉，对于他们来说迁移到React的成本会更高
it was really ads that was kind of using Baltimore it had a higher level investment more people working in that code base that already knew it and more components so it was a harder shift to make
广告团队在我加入之前刚刚用Bolt重写了"广告创建流"模块，花了他们六个月用Bolt代替古老的PHP代码
the ads team just before I joined ads from the mobile team had done a full rewrite of the ads creation flow into bolt which took them I think upwards of six months replacing a very old PHP application with what time was
Blot当时被认为是相当现代的JS框架
considered a very modern JavaScript application but at the same time react
但是与此同时Blot的竞争对手React也开始被用于Facebook的生产项目，而且组建了团队
was also now actually deployed for real on Facebook and had a team that was forming around it
所以现状变成了Facebook内部有两个前端开发框架并存，两个框架解决同一类问题且都有生产应用
so we now had two viable Frameworks that were both live on Facebook both solving real problems
这是不应该的，特别是两个框架的代码相似到会让人分不清哪个是哪个
we shouldn't have two especially two that were similar similar enough to confuse people like if you looked at a code
并且对比两个框架的代码会发现，虽然代码差不多但是它们的工作原理非常不同
their code almost looked identical but that worked really differently it would
如果你需要同时和两个框架打交道，这种情况简直是噩梦，所以我们需要决定谁去谁留
actually be an absolute nightmare if you had to work in both so we had to decide which which to use
[Music]
最终我(Bolt负责人)和Jordan(React创造者)做了一个长长的讨论
a lot of this was ended up being a conversation between myself and Jordan
我们做了很多枯燥的性能测试，尝试找到两个框架应用的边缘案例we did an evaluation of boredom a lot of performance-based stuff and trying to figure out where the edge cases were
React的优势显然在于它能很好地处理复杂性
on the pro side of react obviously there's all the things that we know now it handles complexity way way more even
比如说在用Bolt重写"广告创建流"模块的时候，我们已经出现不得不写出意大利面条代码的情况
when writing the as creation flow in bold we had already hit one place that you just could not do in Bolt without writing spaghetti code and you can do in
但是使用React可以很好解决这个问题，我们认为尽管这种情况可能只会在十个项目中出现一次
react so we knew in the future even if it was only 10 of the experiences we were building we're going to run into this problem again now it might only be
但是当你放大到整个公司，其缺陷也会急速放大
10 unmaintainable but as you scale that across a company that is growing rapidly this becomes an absolute mess
React的缺点是它还没有经过足够多的考验，很多东西当时React根本做不到
the cons of it on the other hand were that react in a lot of ways was not battle tested yet there's a lot of things that simply
比如它不能很好处理表单，文本框
didn't work in react it couldn't handle forms they'd never done a text box and
处理表单元素比如单选按钮时过于复杂，还有就是会不必要地重新渲染大块UI而导致性能问题
there's a lot of complexities around handing awkward form controls like radio buttons and so on that it messed up just performance issues where it would try and re-render large blocks
也就是他们还没来得及做Raact框架的性能优化
so they hadn't had to do all of the performance improvements that obviously exist now
从组织管理角度，另一个对React不利的情况是我们刚刚花了六个月用Bolt重写了业务
on the organizational side that the other con was that we had just done the six-month rewrite in both
Facebook刚刚经历IPO，股市表现不振，挣钱变少
um Facebook had done an IPO recently and the stock had since IPO Facebook wasn't making enough money and
而广告团队又是直接和挣钱相关的团队，钱由这里往下流动
so the ads team is the team that makes you know that's where the money starts
如果我们要再花4个月用React重写Bolt应用，就意味着营收会进一步受影响
if we stop for four months we're gonna have to tell everybody
我们必须对所有人说“对不起，没钱了”，所以是否转向React经历了很多讨论，很难下决定
sorry no money for you so there was a lot of conversation back and forth about all this it was got very difficult
一开始，熟悉Blot的工程师包括Shane，都表示说我们已经在Bolt上投入了太多，而且Bolt使用好好的
initially a lot of the engineers that used bolt including Shane realized just what you said like look we've invested so much in this thing and it's it's really worked for all this stuff
毫无疑问可以继续应对新的挑战
certainly we can work through the next set of challenges we're having so
所以一开始针对全面转向React有一些反对声音
initially there was opposition to react coming in and saying like how are you
反对的人说“这关乎到重要的生意，而React都没有经过足够考验”
gonna you know this new thing that's not even proven yet this is our business this is really important
当我和Jordan讨论的时候，因为双方都对对方的工作背景缺乏了解，所以有很多情绪激动的时刻
when Jordan and I were working through it was definitely uh some emotions uh there um and mostly I think it came from uh each of us having a lack of context of where the other one was coming from so I
出现过各说各话的情况
think there was a lot of talking past each other
最后公司CTO介入，他说："要做正确的技术决定，正确的长期决定，不管最终决定是什么我都会支持"
in the end Mike shroffer stepped in and said look make the right technical decision make the right long-term decision and whatever it is you know I'll back you up
"如果你们需要暂停产品开发四个月，我也会支持你们"
but if you need to pause product development for four months you can
于是我们所有人都聚到一起，讨论了所有相关的问题
we all kind of just got in rooms and you know worked through all these things and got everything out in the air of you know what's a
列出了转变涉及的技术问题，组织问题，财务问题等，最终在大量咖啡的帮助下达成了共识： 转向React
technical problem what's an organization problem what's a financial problem uh and uh kind of a computer understanding eventually um through uh through uh with lots and lots of coffee
决定下达之后，迁移之路却非一帆风顺
that the react was the right way to go but um it was not a straight line at all
Shane(作为Bolt的负责人)成了决定广告业务全面转向React的关键支持者之一
he ultimately was one of the biggest proponents of decision makers and ads switching all over everything to react
这是不常见的，在多数公司如果你的项目和其他项目竞争，你会打压其他项目而不是支持
and that doesn't happen in most companies and most companies if that's your baby project you try to undermine the other the the upstart because you're you know you're really defensive over
但是当时Facebook的风气并不是如此
your own thing that was not the vibe at Facebook at the time and I think that
这一点在Shane身上特别突出
Shane in particular really exemplified that
现在"广告创建流"模块需要用React重写，工作量很大，氛围紧张，广告团队遇到了困难
there was still a lot of work to do on the ads creation flow tensions were mounting and the team was stuck
Jing Chen又一次来救火了
here again to get them unstuck is Jing Chen
当时面临棘手的管理问题，广告团队和开发React的基础设施团队各自内部意见不能统一
we'd have this thorny management issue and a lot of people disagreeing with each other up and down the management chain on both sides of you know in ads and in this product infrastructure group those building react and we'd send Jing
Jing被派去消弭分歧，他们会面以后每个人出来都面带笑容相互拍肩，团队达成了一致
in to talk to the engineers and everyone come out like patting each other on the back full agreement a plan to move forward so she's great at building a
她擅长引导人们达成共识，她能够很快分析出重要的技术细节，统一讨论的对象
consensus because she's able to drill into the important technical details identify them really quickly and and get everyone talking about the same thing
Jing显然帮助了产品建设，而且她还确保每次在React中发现了bug或者不足时，
she obviously helped both build the product but she also made sure that every time we found a bug in react or just something that didn't handle yet
她要么先从产品中抽身直接去修复bug
she either stepped back from products and then just fixed the framework or she
要么安排两到三个工程师工作一个月修复bug，为广告团队扫清障碍
went back to the team and said look we need two or three Engineers working on this stuff for the next month to unblock the ads team
广告业务足够的复杂，它成了一个很好的试验场
the ads manager was complicated enough that it actually ended up being a really great source of
促使React做了很多性能提升，帮助识别出React规模化应用上的痛点
um performance improvements and finding like where are the true points where it does doesn't quite scale
我觉得过程很像玩积木，随着搭建的东西越来越复杂，新的问题不断出现
so I think it was a lot of like you using the building blocks that we had and as you start to assemble them into a really complicated looking application what are the new problems that come out
我们需要解决很多这些新出现的问题
of that way that we need to solve and there was definitely a lot of those this
这是我职业生涯中非常有趣且紧张的一段时间
is one of the most fun intense periods of my career as I remember it we would
我们(React团队)会帮助广告团队实现一些功能
be going to meet with the team and we would have to help them put some feature
我们会先用React自己实现一遍，确保广告团队使用的过程中不会遇到大的困难
in and we would code it up ourselves first and react just to make sure that
或者提前找到他们会遇到的困难，然后提前想出解决方案
the that they wouldn't hit any rough edges or more like to find all the rough edges that we knew they'd hit and figure out what the solutions would be so it
这个过程让人激动，因为我们同时在做两件事，一个是帮助重写对Facebook非常重要的广告管理器软件，
was really exciting because we were working on two things at the same time one was delivering this really complicated really important software
一个是完善React框架自身
project for Facebook uh the ads manager and the other was refining this framework that we really believed in uh which was react
我们花了四个月用React重建了广告管理器，React经历了各种考验和完善
by the time we had rebuilt the ads creation flow which I think took about four months it had been battle tested with basically everything about the
比如支持各种浏览器，支持各种表单字段，有了巨大的性能提升
browser supports all the form fields and everything and also massive performance issues that had been resolved
这时React开源的时机似乎到了
so at that point it was kind of felt that it was ready to be open source
因为我们已经在各种不同的场景使用和验证了它
because you know we we used it in multiple different types of contexts a
我们认为它对外部世界也会有用
nd that uh you know um it would actually be generally useful to the public
[Music]
你刚刚说什么？(空耳，不确定)
Where were you saying?
有煮咖啡吗？
抱歉没有
uh there is not sorry
开源React对我来说从来不是个问题，一开始React的目标就是开源
open sourcing reactor is never a question for me that was the goal from the very beginning
Tom有个理论叫"项目定位"，Facebook从JS世界雇佣了一批先驱开发者但是又不鼓励他们浏览器端开发
Tom had this idea he called it project perception and he was really angry I think it's probably the best word for he's angry that Facebook was
因为当时浏览器端开发被认为比较困难，只有很少的发挥空间
hiring all these luminaries from the JavaScript World they would come to Facebook and you know because we discouraged people from writing client-side JavaScript and because it was a hard environment to maneuver in it
所以这些人会转向移动端开发，因为当时有趣的客户端开发工作在移动端
would actually go pick up mobile because that was where a lot of the interesting client-side development was happening
Tom对此感到不满，他决心扭转这种情况
and Tom was determined to change us around
我记得去参加一次会议，我对一个人说我在Facebook工作，从事JS开发
I remember going to this conference and someone like I was talking to someone and I told them I worked at Facebook on JavaScript and
他问我为什么要为Facebook工作，他说我厌恶Facebook的行为，他们雇佣了优秀的人才，
完成了很棒的项目，但是外部世界对此一无所知，他们只进不出
they're like why would you do that I hate what Facebook does to the JavaScript industry you have hired all these really great people from these really great projects and we have no idea what they're working on now they've given nothing back s
所以当React在内部孵化的时候，我从一开始就说如果项目能成功，我们应该致力于将其开源
so I think when react came along I started very early on talking about if this thing works for us I really want us to find a path to open
我很早就开始对管理层吹风
source and I was running that up the like management chain like very early so
所以当开源的时机成熟时，虽然有一些争议和开会讨论
when the time came to open source it there were some meetings it was controversial
但是我们已经有了开源所需的所有支持
but we had all the support we needed already
开源遇到的第一个技术问题是如何将React从Facebook的基础设施中提取出来，
让它成为一个独立的开源项目
the process of open sourcing uh is interesting there's first a technical problem to solve you have to figure out how to extract it out of your infrastructure and make it work in the open source
这方面我们已经在做Instagram网站的时候做过作业了which is all the homework that we did for Instagram
我们决定开源不能降低原有的开发效率
we made this call that like we will not impact developer productivity at all
开源相关工作将完全由那些主张开源的人来负责处理
it's going to be entirely on the open source team which was just a bunch of people that wanted to open source it to make it work
为了启动开源
then actually pulling the trigger on open source
我们花了很多时间在文档上，解释什么是React，各种概念是什么
we had to write a lot of documentation we spent actually a lot of time with the documentation to explain like hey what is react what are all the concepts and
我们需要想象自己是一个想要构建应用的人，然后思考什么样的文档能够帮助自己
we try to put ourselves in the shoes of like somebody that want to build an app how do we give the documentation in a way it like helps them do that
Paul做了很多文档的工作，他清楚当时需要什么样的生态才能让Rect成功开源
polish Channel as they did a lot of this because he really had the experience with what the ecosystem needed to make this work at the time Apollo fantasy was
Paul和James都是开源的推动者，James是当时Facebook开源负责人，
他刚加入不久，非常希望改变Facebook在开源世界的形象
a huge force on open sourcing as was James Pierce who was the head of  Facebook open source James had joined the company and he really wanted to
change Facebook's open source image we had previously open sourced a lot of
过去我们也开源过一些项目，但是开源以后就不管了，任其腐烂，只为了一个开源的名声
stuff but we let it rot we would say hey we're an open source company here's our great framework and then we would just never maintain it and James and Paul in
James，特别是Paul认为如果要开源就要后续负责，他们的意见起到了重要作用
particular were like pretty instrumental in saying hey if we're going to open source react we're going to do it right
因为我们已经使用React一段时间了，效果不错
internally there was a lot of excitement because we had already been using this thing for a while and it was working for
因此开源React让人激动
us we were excited about it
我们选择JSConf US来推出React，因为这个会议就像JS世界的奥斯卡
we chose jsconf us which was kind of the I don't know the Oscars of JavaScript is that fair representation maybe you know
相关的明星人物会发表演讲，所有人都会关注
all the celebrities are there and everyone's paying attention and
很多人都会在Youtube上观看直播
everybody watches it live on YouTube
Tom和Jordan一起准备了一个演讲
Tom and Jordan put together this presentation
Tom擅长演讲，Jordan技术厉害，就像列侬和麦卡特尼同台演出，成功看起来是注定的
Tom is a great speaker and Jordan is a brilliant engineer it was like Lennon and McCartney type of situation there was no way that this thing could possibly fail
[Music]
JSConf US当天上午9点在佛州举行
it was in Florida um at like 9 00 a.m
而我们在湾区的门洛公园，当天我们起的很早，赶第一班公交到了空荡荡的办公室
We were in Menlo Park and we woke up early we took the first bus into the office it was
我们已经等不及要将React仓库设为公开
completely empty and we're like getting ready to like press the button on the repo to open sources
我和Jordan两人都非常激动地登台
Jordan and I were all excited we got up on stage I'm going
“今天我想介绍一下我们在Facebook如何做JS应用开发”
to talk a bit about how we do JavaScript application development at Facebook it
这次演讲有点特别，我讲了一小部分，Jordan讲了大部分内容
was a little unconventional I like did a little bit of it he did more of it so
“随React发布的还有一种我们称为JSX的嵌入式xml语法”
along with react we are shipping an embeddable XML syntax and we're calling that jsx
我们迫不及待地展示了一段代码，这段代码当时看起来非常奇怪
and we jumped into showing some code and that code looked different it looked weird
"这是React和JSX一起使用的代码"
here we have react used with jsx
人们理所当然地对这种新的开发方式表示了怀疑
and people were rightfully skeptical we'll call it
所有人都表达了厌恶之情，认为这非常糟糕
everyone hated it everyone thought it was awful
[表达厌恶React的推文，偷懒不翻译了]
我们内部本来期待React会有更好的社区反馈
ly we were expecting a much better reception or at least an oh that's
我们期待人们至少会说"有点意思"，期待一些着迷编程语言的人会觉得"我们可以用函数式编程开发UI了"
interesting exception we thought there'd be some language nerds in there who would um think oh I can do fully functional program in the UI oh at least
然而社区的反应像一盆冷水泼过来
that's interesting it was a really humbling experience it was kind of a
对我们来说是一次打击，因为我们牺牲了很多加班和周末才让React能够开源，
然而发布以后每个人都很讨厌它
letdown for us because we had worked nights and weekends on getting this thing open sourceable and then when we go to launch it everyone hated it the
所有的关注点都在JSX，所有人都讨厌它
thing that everyone focuses on is that people really hated jsx
我很久没有回顾这段经历了，让我看看...
I haven't watched this video in a while see
"这些div不是你熟悉的dom节点"
these divs are not exactly what you're used to they're not Dom nodes
“它们是特别的React元素，我待会会讲到为什么这种区分是重要的”
so they're special reactives and I'll get to why that's important
我不记得当时有注意到人们的负面反应，完全不记得
I don't remember thinking that they were hating it I don't remember at all thinking that
不记得当时他们发了那么多厌恶React的推文
they were like tweeting a bunch of a bunch of stuff
对，这个就是当时的ppt，我们当时没有做任何铺垫，没有说是要解决什么问题
this is the slide for sure we haven't talked about any problems we're trying to solve we
也没有解释为什么这个方式对我们有效，或者React的设计哲学是什么
haven't talked about why this is working for us or what were the principles of design
我们就直接展示了一段包含xml的JS代码，所有人都表示WTF?
we're just like boom here's some XML in your JavaScript and people are like hey what is happening
可怜的Jordan
uh poor Jordan
我们没有意识到当时Facebook和JS世界其他部分之间的落差有多么大
what we didn't really fully understand was how big of a Delta there was between where the rest of the world was in the JavaScript community and where Facebook was
我并不责怪当时批评的人，我也不觉得批评我们疯狂的人自身是疯子
I don't blame them I don't think anybody who tweeted Facebook is crazy was crazy themselves
我觉得他们是对的，当时我们是有点疯狂
I think they were they were kind of right we were a little crazy
[狗狗：你终于承认了]
对于个人来说，演讲发布后某个时刻我觉得通过开源让我们更加融入社区的努力失败了
I think there was a moment for me personally where I felt like you know my goal with the open sourcing of this was to get us closer to the
并且我们反而退步了，我们可能对外界展示了我们根本不知道自己在做什么
community and I may have set us back a step I may have demonstrated that we actually have no idea what we're doing
因为我们做的事情和社区做的事情如此不同
because what we're doing is so much different than what the rest of the community was doing
内部总结就是"好吧，我们搞砸了"，“失策了”
and internally there was a well we messed that up we made the wrong call
因为我认为衡量成功的标志应该是"Wow，Facebook正在做一些非常酷的东西"
um because I think the measure of success would have been wow Facebook engineering is doing some really cool stuff
而不是"Facebook不知道自己在做什么"
and instead it was Facebook engineering has no idea what they're doing
我记得从那以后，Jordan好几年都没再参加JS会议
I think that gsconf um appearance might have been Jordan's last conference for a good few years I
Tom也一段时候没有再参加，React的发布演讲不知何故变成了黑粉们的盛宴
think camokino didn't go back for a while as well it turned into a bit of a
特别是对于React来说，它创新，有用，是提升开发者效率的一个礼物
troll Fest for no good reason and particularly for something that was as an Innovative and useful and you know just fantastic for developer productivity and just it's literally a gift to everybody here here move faster
然而却遭到误解，承受恶名，特别是这些负面反应都是条件反射式的，未经过认真思考的
for free to have people misunderstand it and say all these bad things about it that were just you know knee-jerk reactions without actually having taken time to think about it
Tom和Jordan对此感到挫败，特别是他们二人在过去的两年中也在Facebook内部遭遇过误解
um can only must have felt very bad especially because both Jordan and Tamil had already gone through all this internally in Facebook for two years but
但是在Facebook你可以有充分表达解释的机会，然而对于整个世界来说第一印象更加重要
inside in Facebook it's a smaller scale you can just get in a meeting room and talk about it um but you can't really do that with the whole world can you
React的一些核心设计原则在Facebook内部是不言自明的
there were some technical decisions that were made as hard to react that were self-evident
但是对于Facebook之外的受众来说则显得非常疯狂
within Facebook but were like crazy when when um given to a different audience in the community
所以编程中有这样一种叫做"关注点分离"的思想
so there was this notion of separation of concerns
当时流行的做法是不同文件做分离，
也就是你不应该把JS/CSS/HTML放在同一个文件里，而是应当每种类型内容一个文件
at the time like you didn't you shouldn't put your HTML CSS and JavaScript into the same file like should I really extract them out and you should like uh like have
当时这种分离思想被认为是最佳实践
this separation and so this was like very like the best practice at the time
而React践行的"关注点分离"与此不同
what was interesting about the approach to separation concerns in react is that
在React中我们通过组件来做逻辑关注点的分离
you separate your concerns into different components so rather than
对比来说，此前一个项目会按照视图和模型做关注点分离，
Reactsaying I have my view concerns over here and my model concerns over here
而现在React会按照功能来分离不同的关注点，
比如这些组件对应新闻流功能，这些是相册相关的，那些是实现管理员面板的
you say you have your news feed concerns over here your photo concerns over here your admin panel concerns over here
也就是关注点分离的方式发生了变化
so it's a different way of separating concerns and
React发布之后有很多人反对，一些人认为那些推出React的人都是小丑
so there was like a lot of backlash around like oh those people at Facebook are clowns like they don't know how to write software and everything
当时我们认为React在Facebook之外可能不会有发展前景
we thought that react probably had no future outside of Facebook
[Music]
对于主张开源React的人来说似乎所有的希望都落空了
it looked like all hope was lost for our friends at the Facebook office but
然而随着Facebook之外有人开始尝试React，转机出现了
fortunately someone outside of Facebook was willing to give it a chance
foreign
[Music]
2013年我开始使用React的时候它在社区中还不流行
when I first started using react in 2013 it was not popular in the community it had just
当时React刚刚在一次JS会议上发布，我是在Hacker News上了解到的
been announced at jsconf I saw the announcement post on Hacker News
我立即意识到它会对我当时做的一个项目有所帮助and immediately thought that it would be helpful for one of the projects that I was working on at the time
那时我正在为可汗学院开发一个交互式的数学问题编辑器，项目的架构是面向组件的
I was building an interactive math question editor at Khan Academy and it was something that had a very component oriented architecture
我当时使用的是Backbone.js
I was trying to use backbone.js at the time
但是渐渐发现状态管理越来越难
and found that the state management was getting a little bit hard
当我审视React的时候，我发现它似乎解决了当时我所面临的问题
and when I looked at react I thought to myself wow this actually looks like it solves a lot of the problems that I have right now
我正在看的这篇贴文是我2013年写的，当时我才接触React，刚开始使用它一周左右
I'm looking at this post from 2013 that I guess I wrote a week after I learned about react and it was right after I had
有人在Quora上提问: "如何评价Facebook的React框架?"
started trying to use it and somebody had asked how is Facebook's react
虽然才用了几天，我还是决定根据自己的体验回答这个提问
JavaScript library and I was a few days into using it and so I decided to write an answer to that question based on my experience
我的回答非常正面，我记得我当时认为React真的解决了我的需求，
the answer I wrote is very positive I think I was having a really good time using it and it was solving my needs really well
其中一段是这么说的：
"我刚刚使用React重写了一个两千行代码的项目，并向React提交了好几个PR"
None line from the post says I just rewrote a 2000 line project in react and have now made a handful of
"目前接触到的所有方面都感觉经过了深思熟虑，很骄傲能成为第一个非Facebook的React生产用户"
pull requests to react everything about react I've seen so far seems really well thought out and I am proud to be the first non-facebook production user of
接着我又谈到了一些技术细节，以及React是如何帮助我的，这个回答现在看起来就像是一颗时光胶囊
react and I talked a little bit more about some of the technical details and how it was helping me it's cool to look back and it's almost a bit of a time
它记录下了当时我激动的心情，尽管那时我才使用React一周时间，而这份激动持续了很长时间
capsule to see how even one week into react being released I was already pretty excited about it and I think that excitement lasted for a long time
接着我将当时手上所有的项目都用React重写了一遍
I converted my entire code base that I was working on at the time over to react
结果是代码量减少，更容易理解，而且性能更好
I think it ended up being less code and it was easier to understand and it was faster
很快我就决定继续使用React并将其部署到生产环境
pretty quickly I said Okay I want to keep using react and I ended up deploying that to production
我用React重写的项目应该是React在Facebook之外的第一次生产环境部署
my my Rewritten code and that was I think the first production code using react outside of Facebook
foreign
it was a brand new project that had just been open sourced and not many people
had used it before and so there were a bunch of rough edges it seemed like you
know maybe nobody had tried to use it in a particular way before or if something
just wasn't documented well enough and I was trying to use it a slightly
different way than it was intended I ran into these little bugs or issues where
it didn't work quite as I was expecting it to for some of those I read through the source code and tried to figure out
okay why isn't this working is there anything that I can be doing differently
for other cases I ended up joining the IRC chat Channel where a lot of the core
team members were hanging out after it had been open sourced
that helped me get started not just using react but also starting to
contribute to it as I started filing issues and helping other people who were
in that chat room as well as starting to make small code changes and starting to
improve react over time her perspective from you know Khan Academy and just
being outside of Facebook was so valuable so helpful so if he started as
someone using react externally then sort of like moved on to being
someone who contributed to react core externally then became the most
significant contributor to react core then we would have these like weekly
team meetings and invite Sophie to come and so Sophie like worked out with her
local manager at her company to like carve out Friday afternoons to come to
Facebook and hang out with us and so determined not to do what we had done
previously where we hired folks from the open source community and then they
never contributed anything back she became like the the first ever like open source recruited member of the team
Sophie's involvement lifted the spirits
of the react team it also got them thinking that maybe just maybe the rest
of the ecosystem had just misreact unfairly they had something special they
knew it what they didn't know was how to convince everyone else
I think there are people on the team like me and Jordan and Tom and
christadeau who like the The Challenge and the the competitive nature of it we
knew that this was good technology and I was so sure of that that um
you know I viewed it as just a a messaging problem you know okay we gotta
crack how we message this to people because they don't get it and we have to
figure out how to how to bring them there
the open source feels like a milestone and it feels like this is the end my
impressive is just the beginning because when you open social actually have zero
users now you need to actually like build a community uh get all of the bug
fixed like make sure it actually solves the use case for the people and so this
is like when the Journey Begins we buckle down we and we we also realized I
think that really when you have a project like this that's
um different you have to convince people one by one
so I think that's really what we focused on and we learned a lot doing that we
learned that the ideas in reactor are solid but
really the ideas are not what people encounter when they adopt a framework
what they encounter are the docs and the error messages what they need more than
anything else when they adopt something is an incremental way of doing that
so the team got to work they focused on spreading the knowledge of react one
concept at a time one person at a time then an opportunity arose
another conference later the same year thank goodness Pete
gave a talk at jsconf EU I had my desk over by the um by the product infrastructure team I was sitting next
to Tomo and he's like oh we're just like sponsoring this JS conf EU conference
and like we have to give a keynote and like I don't want to give it because I
think he was like he didn't want to go through all that stuff because you know after you give the talk like people go
and yell at you after you get off stage and you go to the happy hour and stuff
it's like it's not not the most Pleasant thing in the world and I was like I'll
do it um I'll take the free trip to Berlin and
go uh give a talk at a conference hey I'm Pete uh I'm gonna talk to you about
a library for creating user interfaces that we call react
and we open source this at jsconfus a couple months ago and we got some kind
of sarcastic responses on Twitter a little bit of snickering that kind of
thing um we weren't really communicating what
we were doing um so I'd like to talk to you today
about the design decisions um around react uh what we're doing
differently than other Frameworks and kind of the implementation that lets us
make these decisions and make it really fast for this talk it was like here's what
makes react different I'm not even trying to say it's good I'm not even
trying to say you should use it I'm trying to say that this is interesting
and there's a lot of interesting stuff about how this thing works that you
should pay attention to and
um that really resonated with people and so we got these kind of early innovators
you know if you think of the crossing the chasm
diagram where you've got your your early adopters and then you've got your
laggers and in the middle you have your kind of normal companies that talk
really got those early adopters fired up and evangelized and react inside of
their own companies after Pete's talk interest started to pick up people
started paying attention they just wanted to you know let me let me just
see if there's something there and so we got this kind of like Slow Burn of
adoption of react and it prompted some really interesting conversations it
recruited Brandon Bloom into the community who came from the functional
programming World somewhere he started
talking to his friends and said hey I
think this like react thing is actually worth paying attention to and then he
goes and talks to his friend David Nolan who is this very well known very well
respected really great musician and JavaScript developer I think he was
working at the New York Times at the time and I was passing through New York
to do something and it grabbed coffee and I asked Pete some questions and
Brandon Brandon Bloom that was my friend that said you should really look at
react and the reason I was excited about it more than I think you could have been
if you were JavaScript developer JavaScript is kind of multi-paradigm you
can do object oriented you can do functional if you want but it's not
required but in closure enclosure script functional is the most idiomatic thing
and nothing existed like we were sort of like always trying to get things to work
but it was always felt like there was friction I was like
still early in my career right and this is like really senior super smart
engineer and it was the type of thing where like he would ask me questions
about it and I would like stumble to explain it and I would explain it poorly
and then he would repeat it back to me in like a super eloquent great way and I
was like yes I'm gonna steal that and so when I sat with Brandon and Pete it was
like this huge light bulb went off I was like finally this is so Random uh
Facebook made this functional UI framework Eureka I mean it was
definitely a Eureka moment it it did allow closure script programmers to
finally write a reasonably performant functional uis and it was very natural
it was a very very good fit like a week or two later he wrote this blog post
called the future of JavaScript mvcs that just like changed the trajectory of
the project in many ways you look at react and
you're like there's no way this could be fast there's no way it could be
efficient and then I showed like you know these diagrams of what um backbone
and react ohm look like and react is much better especially when you're using
persistent data structures so my article I think was focusing purely on the
technical benefits of the design it removed The Superficial consideration
and I think people started saying okay I will try it not I'm going to use it but
it removed that I'm never going to use that too oh I'll give it a shot this is
interesting once that post came out like within three months after that I would
say that we were one of the big contenders if you were picking a
JavaScript framework if you want to spread an idea you need to really
convince a few people and have those people share your message
you can't just be shouting at yourself more people started to realize that
react some good ideas and made UI development
simpler in a lot of ways over the course of the next I would say like year or two
we're kind of just tracking things like you know like Google Alerts of how many
times is it being mentioned who's writing about it what projects are
cropping up um because react was very unopinionated
about a lot of stuff that you need in order to build a front-end web application and you know people would
fill in the blanks and there was a bunch of State Management libraries that
cropped up and there was a bunch of you know router libraries that cropped up
and server-side rendering strategies and so there was this sort of Slow Burn of
adoption over the next year or two react is a small focused UI library but it
proved capable when tackling Facebook's hardest problems in other big companies
noticed but there was one company especially eager to rethink best practices
[Music]
we first heard about react back in 2014 the Netflix website had been built using
Java web uh it was very slow it took about 15 minutes to get up a build and
we decided to move to a more modern framework there we go now at the time we
weren't quite sure if you know this react thing was going to work out it was
kind of new and so we were very apprehensive especially since we were
building the future of the next 10 years of the website right you know we make a
bad choice now we got to backtrack um you know years worth of work and so
we were very careful about you're not jumping into something that was too
bleeding edge and so what they did was they actually
pitted two teams against each other each was given 30 days to build a prototype
with one being react and the other one being backbone and after 30 days the
choice was clear so thank you all for coming out tonight
we're really excited to have you here and share the learnings that we've had
building the new UI in react for the past year it was not this stage it was our next
stage over where I gave my react presentation back I guess in 2015.
same feeling like oh my goodness I've got to convince all these people that
react is amazing um but I guess it worked so as part of
the team that built the new site using react at first it was very clunky like
you're writing components and they're not quite you know you're putting too
much logic into them or you're thinking too big it's not clear the difference in
the Paradigm and then you start to use it and you go okay wait wait wait I'm
thinking much more Atomic hence the symbol of react I'm thinking about this
in individual reusability okay now I'm thinking about the testability of these
components I'm seeing the benefits now come out of it I can reuse this over
here we can test this over here we can change this here we can add props in
here and it becomes very exciting to see that new paradigm come to play and go
this is going to be revolutionary this is going to change the world let's go
back in time one year to the old Netflix UI you guys might remember this one the
overall look and feel is kind of like this old DVD kind of box art feel and so
I actually want to show you one of the early prototypes of what we thought the
new UI would look like we knew that going forward the world was changing web
was changed changing things were moving faster and our competition was moving
faster as well so choosing react and going with a more modern framework
really helped us accelerate how fast we could build the website how fast we
could get new changes that door how fast we could try improvements for our
customers to make the best possible experience and because of that we've been at the
Forefront of leading what UI design looks like in terms of web development
we've had a lot of companies copy us which we take is a great compliment but
we were there first because of react and its ability to move so quickly in terms of design
this is how it ended up turning out and this is a UI that's big and immersive and completely built in react so we're very very proud of it and the result
[Music]
Netflix was now praising react publicly and with a second big company betting
big on react the framework grew in popularity in fact it kind of took on a
life of its own and the community started to take off
[Music]
react at this point was getting more popular and somebody on Twitter mentioned like
hey it would be cool to have like a react conference and a lot of people started like uh commenting and tweeting
and everything about this and uh I went to my manager tomokino and he was like there's like 50 tweets about react today
like people are talking about organizing conferences should we organize a conference and I was like I don't know
what that means I don't know how to do that but like maybe I was very post
doing a conference um I thought it was very cool that we got so much traction
without really pouring marketing money into it even though react came from big
tech company Juggernaut Facebook it was a small group of people that were like
really dedicated to seeing this thing succeed so it felt like this very Indie
you know Rebel Alliance type of project and so I was like we don't need a user
conference like with like we got this Cool vibe going on like let's see how
far we can push it I was totally wrong we had said to ourselves I think it
would be fun to host a react conference but are there even enough people using
react who would want to go to that and eventually we decided Well let's try it
let's try to host the conference and see how it goes
within a minutes all of the tickets were sold out and we actually crashed the
website that we are handled for like the actual payment system and everything
trap the CTO of Facebook actually like reach out to me saying like hey I have
this very important like VP or CTO or like of some company that one scene that
couldn't get in like hey can you do as a favor and I was like I would love to
like kill the CTO and everything but like you know like we're like completely
booked certainly we were very surprised about how quickly the tickets had sold
out we didn't realize just how much the react ecosystem had grown and just how
much enthusiasm had been created by early adopters
foreign
[Music]
quickly as far as conference planning goes and we just had it on campus in one
of our cafes and we you know bus people from the nearest hotel and it was very very under produced
um but it worked out really really well good morning everyone and welcome to react Jessica
the conference when they're like extremely extremely well as the
organizer of the conference I'm so excited to be here and we open source
like a bunch of our projects like so react native and we started talking
about graphql about three day and so yeah it's been a massive success there
is this moment where you go and you see the stage and it's like there's a giant wood cut out like logo of the react atom and
I was like my friend Michael the designer at Instagram drew that in front
of me like in the middle of the night before we were going to open sources
thing because we needed a logo and I was like Michael just like throw something
together real quick and like now it's this thing that has somebody has built a
giant sign with this on it and there's something about the physical impact of
that that's really cool that was the moment when it dawned on me that react
was becoming something different you know so for a long time what react
was to me was a software project and the reason why I wanted people to
adopt it was because I really thought it would make their software better and
make their lives better and make their on-call rotations better there are a lot
of reasons why I thought it would help them after that conference what I realized is
that react was becoming a community there was meetups that would happen the
immediate next week that would have an expanded audience that they could go
deeper into some of the things that were discussed was really really cool and a
huge recognition for us that the community was going to be
an incredible part of what would make react work and had at that point was
definitely already a really important part of what had gotten react to that point so far
[Music]
it's proven to me that uh engaging with your open source Community is is
actually more important than the technical work itself like if you don't
have a community you don't have an open source project I'm excited that we just
continue rethinking best practices I want to thank this community for making
it possible for us to keep investing in this and keep working on it
um that's all I got thanks it was a real high point for not just
for me but for the team and you know I think for Facebook engineering I think
we really felt like not just validated but like we were
actually like doing something that people cared about
and it was a really really good feeling it was already like more widely used
within the company but now it was like okay how do we like actually start
converting everything to react how do we like remove and deprecate like all of
the other Frameworks and really like double down on react oh hey I was going
going from like an interesting product to like this is the next big thing so it
was really like a really amazing time to be around and to like really like get
the whole company like working together as one uh you know to like make this happen
let's see I have some keepsakes up here which will be not easy for me to get down but
let's see I have some stickers oh this is a fun one this is the first ever react die cut sticker
we ordered like a bunch of these and put them on our laptops and I just I never
wanted to use the last one that I had Facebook open source stickers
oh some of these will be a trip down memory lane for folks react conf we made
you know 2018 Facebook open source
it's a good one react conf attendee badge this was a book uh from the original
react.js conf at Facebook's headquarters so this had a list of the speakers and
the schedule and um here's the Keynote and Christopher shadow
we had all sorts of swag made and a bunch of other stuff so pretty good stuff
pretty good memories dated with questions from the community and a new developer enters reacts orbit
[Music]
what should I do with my hands so you're saying that I should actually
uh start like uh let me Focus for a second just for the record I did not
create react react was created by Jordan walk
I worked at a small startup we were creating a sort of a digital publishing
platform so there was a really complex post editor with different blocks or
like a scrollable text with like different effects and stuff and so uh
creating a dynamic kind of interactive editor for for these things was really
difficult and we returned it with backbone I kind of wanted to give react
a try because it was supposed to solve this problem the first react component I wrote was a
like button so it was just like a button you click it and it says like you like
this or you and somebody like this or you and like 40 others like this so
there was a bit of like a split and logic and then the way you would Express
this in uh like in other Frameworks at the time uh like you had you had to kind
of manually like watch what's changed and like update it and in react you
could just say if nobody liked this show this if one person like this show this
otherwise show this and like it's a very natural way to write this kind of code
and yeah I just wrote that button and I was like yeah that looks good ship it
and so we actually rewrote the entire app in react over the course of like 90
months while still shipping new features so react speed up our development so
much that we were able to add new features faster at the same time as we
were replacing old features that's why I really kind of fell in love with it
a lot of things didn't exist back then like there was no such thing as a react
ecosystem so if you needed something it didn't exist you'd have to write it
so like you'd have to figure out how to do it because otherwise you're not going
to have a product right so that's kind of what I did for a bunch of things
one of those projects in particular was
uh
like I just saw like a big opportunity there it was called react hot loader at the
time so I wanted to give a talk about that somebody else has done a talk that
mentioned it earlier at reactant a really clever fellow called Damn abramov
figured this out and he created the react hotloader and I felt that well
then that just wouldn't be interesting because people kind of already saw it
which in retrospect I don't think it would be true but that's how I saw it at
the time so I wanted to kind of spice it up a little bit and I wanted to make a
proof of concept of a thing I saw in breath Victor's demo that is often
referred to as time traveling you're designing something embedded in
time you need to be able to control time you need to be able to see across time
otherwise you're designing blind I didn't really know how to do it but I
thought that's a cool idea for a talk so I'm gonna send the proposal if the
proposal is successful then I'll just figure it out and it turned out that the
proposal was more successful than I thought it would be and so I made a
proof of concept for that and that approval concept became known as Redux
so my talk is about developer tools because react and hotel ordering and
time travel these are all developer tools he was like literally creating
Redux in service of being able to deliver this this talk and I called it
presentation driven development because the Thing That Shook out of it was you
know this sort of like canonical State Management library for react apps for
for several years most of my work is around the react ecosystem because
that's what inspired me to contribute to the open source in the first place but
there are two particular projects that I'm going to talk about today it was
very validating to give that talk
but I was not surprised by the response because well I I had my
doubts but also I thought the talk was good like I thought it's a really good talk
and I was glad that people also liked it but I think it was actually not the talk
that was uh that was really like the moment for me I think it was just like
being there I kind of felt like you know like like
going to Hogwarts for the first time I think it kind of had this uh this
feeling because there were all these people who I only knew them as these
avatars and when I season meet somebody in person they they kind of become
three-dimensional of course you kind of see the whole picture and I think it was
just like such a wholesome feeling is the feeling that we are all trying to
figure out what we can do with this thing and we don't know it yet and we're
just playing with it that's also where I met jinchan I asked
for for her advice before because she's one of the co-creators of the fox
architecture so it was nice to meet her in person and she mentioned that
actually Facebook is hiring in London and so they arranged an interview for me
right at the conference which was like our normal interview process the same I
think like four interviews or something like this but I I missed the second day
of the conference but we just did an interview there and so that's kind of
how I got into Facebook we just quickly grabbed them out of the
conference a little bit like on the down low and then uh conducted the interviews
um in the basement of a hotel I think is that normal entries no Dan is so special
he's always been all special I guess like I would think of myself as like
maybe the first member of what would become the react
team as you know it today because I joined a little bit earlier than I think
Andrew Brian Luna and and like a bunch of other people who work with us now and
I joined at the time when a few people who worked with us before were just
about to leave so I was kind of in this transitional period when the team was changing a lot
foreign
[Music]
do you remember the first time you met Andrew
uh I think I've met I think I met him yeah well that was the
clear moment maybe was that the first time we actually did you get invited to
react conf because of that he had a speech
I met him like I think before that I met you and Sophie and Joe and Tim like all
in the same week yeah he started asking some questions that were very similar to
the questions that on the team we were talking about internally and so I just
remember like I gotta connect you with like Sebastian and Jordan and the rest
of the team yeah and then also I was like to the recruiters I was like yeah
this guy like we gotta hire this Andrew guy and I think we were really fortunate
early on to have a bunch of people liking that kind of stepped up and they
were like this seems cool I just want to be a part of this I just want to help
I didn't realize it was kind of like a freshman class sort of feeling at the
time started managing the team around that time as well
um and like I couldn't have really asked for a better uh both project and like a
set of colleagues and team to to join the beginning of phase two yeah that's cool
[Music]
like man we're nailing this
react was now out of the hands of its Founders it was ready to take on New
Life in the care of a new community grown and future-minded team we tried to
watch some of the numbers like the number of GitHub stars or the number of
npm downloads on Google Trends how many people are searching for react and none
of those numbers are perfect but basically all of them kept going up over
time and eventually got to a point where we looked at it and said oh yeah like
millions of people essentially are using react there are a lot of little details
in how we did things that encourages an ecosystem to participate that were
critical Parts on making it what it is today we didn't put everything in the
framework we left a lot of it to the ecosystem to innovate and we got a lot
of contributions we got a lot of interest that way we got a lot of things
spurring from that it was not ever a foregone conclusion I like it's still
surreal to me that it's as popular as it is it's this great example of this like
Underdog technology within a big company where there could have been these forces
that really pushed back on it I think a lot of elements of good timing Good
Fortune good luck good leadership support all sort of like aggregated to
allow react to be a success that had we missed a few of those or had a handful
more things failed instead of succeeded then I do not think react would be in
the spot that it is today I feel like you can't take anyone out of
it and have it be what it became I think in the early days obviously Jordan right
like this thing wouldn't exist and then Jing Chan just absolutely critical I
mean she was so instrumental in the early days of react that it just
wouldn't have been a thing that we cared about if it didn't prove itself
and then Shane O'Sullivan is responsible for you know really I mean a very hard
decision to like I'm gonna go this path instead of that thing and then the
engineers that worked on refining and iterating on it and turning it into
something good it was Chateau and Paul shantacy and Pete hunt and my manager
Adam wolf when I was like you know asking all these questions about like
should we be do like is this even worth it especially after JS conf when we were
feeling defeated you know he was there to pick me back up and be like no look
it is delivering value this is good keep going and there's different phases too
right you have the early early days and you had the like for the next literally
almost we're going on 10 years now with Sebastian's technical leadership and
Andrew and Dan and Dominic and flarney and Sophie and I I just feel like it's
just a group of incredible people and if you take any of them out of it
it just looks pretty different it was really a team effort
uh it was really a team effort from the very beginning
[Music]
says that awesome Solutions are rarely created by large organizations it's
almost always one person with passion and vision that slowly start to infect
others this is this is a great summary of how react became react because it was
never inevitable it was always this wild idea that kept Gathering momentum person
by person and any expected react to fail and if it weren't for the hard work of a
few determined developers it very well could have
this is just the beginning of the react story the story of how a community
transformed an underdog UI Library into the most popular JavaScript framework
today this is react podcast I'm fantastic
[Music]
thank you I'm like so tempted to just prize FaceTime Jordan right now be like
interview it's just really strange to think that
you're just so close to death the first reactive shirt that we made
thousands of developers find jobs across Europe using Honeypot if you're up for a
new challenge in one of these European cities sign up at honeypot.io
if you want to see more Tech documentaries then subscribe so you don't miss the next one
[Music]